Guide to the New-York Historical Society Museum Department Records 1765, 1830-2018 NYHS-RG 20
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Exhibitions, 1941-2018; 84.58 Linear feet
  The Exhibitions series includes files related to the planning and presentation of exhibitions at N-YHS, especially for the 1980s and later, though there are a few files for the 1970s and earlier. The bulk of the files include documentation compiled from various sources within the Museum Department of specific exhibitions. Although the specific content varies widely by exhibition, documents can include checklists, images, loan documentation, publicity material, research files, comment books, wall texts and labels, design elements, budgets and funding requests, and other like matter. Not all exhibitions are represented in the series and some are very lightly documented. On the other hand, several are more extensively documented, such as the traveling exhibition of the Audubon watercolors in the 1990s. The bulk of the files relate to installed exhibitions, but some proposed exhibitions are also included, perhaps most notably the files for the planning of a 1990s exhibition concerning the Tenth Street Studio Building.
  Files related to exhibitions were transferred to the archives over time by various members of the museum staff. Consequently, important exhibition files can be found in other Museum series, especially the Curatorial and the Collections Management series.
  The series is organized in the following subseries:
  Subseries II.A. General Files
  Subseries II.B. Audubon Traveling Exhibition
  Subseries II.C. Jack Rutland and Margaret Tamulonis Files
  Subseries II.D. Kimberly Orcutt Files
  Generally, the General Files are the records of individual exhibitions that appear to have been compiled from various sources and were organized together by the processing archivist. The Rutland/Tamulonis and Orcutt subseries include the files of particular individuals that include records of various exhibitions.
  - Subseries II.A. General Files, 1941-2018; 71.75 Linear feet
    The subseries includes files that appear to have been compiled over time for the purpose of documenting various aspects of particular exhibitions presented at N-YHS. The subseries includes only a few folders of material from before 1970. An increased number of files appear for the 1970s and early 1980s, and these appear to be largely from the files of the curator at that time, Mary Black. The bulk of the files date from after 1982 and seem to have come from various sources within the Museum Department (which included the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture collections in the 1990s), including curators, collections management/registrar, researchers, and others. In addition to installed exhibitions, the files also include some proposed exhibitions that never took place.
    The type of documentation present for each exhibition is highly uneven, ranging from one folder with a document or two to extensive documentation of various aspects of an exhibition. Typical documentation found for many of the exhibitions includes checklists or other object lists, loan agreements and receipts, and publicity material. Other textual documents that can be found for many exhibitions are installation and design descriptions, wall and label text, conservation notes, budgets, grant or other funding proposals, correspondence/printed emails, and other planning documents. There are a few public comment books and the container list notes when these are in an exhibition's files. Some exhibitions include the sometimes extensive research files of the curator, public historian, or other exhibition developer. For traveling exhibitions, there is some documentation concerning arrangements and logistics.
    In terms of images, there is a noticeable contrast between the files before and after circa 2003. Some exhibition files from the 1970s-1990s have object photographs and several have color slides of the installed galleries. The gallery slides are exceptional enough that an attempt was made by the archivist to identify them and note them in the container list. In the early 2000s, with the emergence of workplace digital technology, images become more common in the files. Many files from this later period have object lists with "thumbnail" sized color images. The press/publicity materials commonly include a professionally-produced CD with the paper material. Informally-created CDs from curators, researchers, conservators, and others are in the files, though not all are well-labeled as to content. Similarly, some of the later exhibitions have CDs of audio tours and other exhibition-related matter. Some of these CDs (and DVDs) are noted in the container list, but most are not because of their increasingly common presence (and often unclear content).
    The subseries is arranged in chronological order, based on the opening year of the exhibition. Generally only that year is shown in the container list although there are likely to be earlier or later documents in the file.
    Note on labels: Many of the folders in the boxes are labeled with shorthand or working titles, not the full final exhibition title. Some of the folder labels in a set even refer to different titles, and planning documents commonly refer to various titles. The container list below attempts to smooth these differences by referring as often as possible to the full final name of the exhibition and by providing any alternative titles in a note. Nonetheless, researchers should be alert to the possibility of disconnects between the title as shown in the container list and the exhibition's actual title as they know it, as well as disconnects between the title in the container list and that on the physical folders.
    Access Restrictions
    Most or all of these files are expected to be stored off-site and so require advance notice in order to access them.
    - Former Governors and Mayors; 19th Century Hotels, Undated (Offsite-box 195, Folder 1)
      Includes summary description of two exhibitions, date unknown.
    - American Scenes & Events on Textiles, 1941 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 2)
      Includes only a photocopy of the catalogue.
    - 250th Anniversary of Trinity Church, 1947 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 3)
    - American Presentation Silver, 1947 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 4)
      Includes curatorial object notes. Document was transferred to the record group in November 2017 from the Miscellaneous Manuscripts/American Historical Manuscripts Collection where it had been filed under S for silver.
    - Country Houses on Manhattan Island, 1952 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 5)
    - The New York "El", 1955 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 6)
    - Rediscovered Painters of Upstate New York (2 folders), 1959 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 7-8)
    - Various, 1960s (Offsite-box 195, Folder 9)
      Includes label text for Incas of Peru and other unidentified exhibitions.
    - Eye on the City: The Photographer in New York, 1970 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 10)
    - City of Promise: Aspects of Jewish Life in New York, 1971 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 11)
    - Sculpture Show, 1972? (Offsite-box 195, Folder 12)
    - New York to the Eve of Revolution, 1973 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 13)
    - New York, The New Empire: John Pintard and His Society, 1974 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 14)
    - American Silhouette (2 folders), 1974 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 15-16)
    - Manhattan Now: 14 Photographers Look at the Form of the Old City (12 folders), 1974 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 17-28)
    - Moving: 300 Hundred Years of Transportation in New York (3 folders), 1976 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 29-31)
    - Shakers in New York State (3 folders), 1975 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 32-34)
    - New York Cabinetmaker and His Use of Space (7 folders), 1976 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 35-41)
    - Op Sail (6 folders), 1976 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 42-47)
    - Remember the Ladies, 1977 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 48)
    - 200 Years of American Illustration, 1976 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 49-50)
    - Fashions and Facades: Photographs by William Cunningham, 1976 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 1)
    - The Dutch Republic in the Days of John Adams, 1976 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 2)
    - New York Then and Now: Photographs of New York in the Past and Present, 1977 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 3)
    - Think Small (2 folders), 1978 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 4-5)
    - The Art of the Conservator: New Life for Old Objects (2 folders), 1978 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 6-7)
    - Street Kids (Children's Aid Society) (3 folders), 1978 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 8-10)
    - Artists and Architects of the New York Subway (2 folders), 1979 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 11-12)
    - Artists and Architects of the New York Subway. Oversize, 1979 (Box 274, Folder 10)
      Includes a decal for the #6 New York City subway line.
    - By a Child's Hand Wrought, 1979 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 13)
    - Proposed Exhibition. Magna Carta, 1979 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 14)
    - 55 Wall Street: A Working Landmark (Citibank) (9 folders), 1980 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 15-23)
    - Tiffany Silver (6 folders), 1980 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 24-29)
    - Small Folk: A Celebration of Childhood in America (2 folders), 1980 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 30-31)
    - That Belmont Look (3 folders), 1980 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 1-3)
    - The Phrenology of the Land: How to Read the Topography of New York Province and State (2 folders), 1980 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 4-5)
    - The Mayor's House: Gracie Mansion (2 folders), 1981 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 6-7)
    - Collaboration: Artists & Architects, 1981 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 8)
    - Exhibition Proposal. 200th Anniversary of Episcopal Diocese of New York (Offsite-box 197, Folder 9)
    - Cast With Style: 19th Century Cast Iron Stoves from the Albany Area (2 folders), 1982 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 10-11)
    - Cancelled Exhibition. Gustav Stickley and the American Arts & Crafts Ideal, 1982 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 12)
    - Sailing Ships in Dutch Prints: Four Centuries of Naval Art from the Rijksmuseum, 1982 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 13)
    - Breaking Ground: Open Spaces Temporary & Accidental, 1982 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 14)
    - Exhibition Proposal. Britain Salutes New York / British Travelers in New York, 1982 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 15)
    - The Birth of New York: Nieuw Amsterdam (13 folders), 1982 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 16-28)
    - Manhattan Observed: 14 Photographers Look at New York (3 folders), 1982 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 29-31)
    - Oom-Pah-Pah: The Great American Brass Band (12 folders), 1982 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 1-12)
    - Oom-Pah-Pah: The Great American Brass Band. Oversize, 1982 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 17)
      Includes a poster.
    - Grand Central Terminal: City Within the City (2 folders), 1982 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 13-14)
    - Proposed Exhibition. Iroquois in New York State, 1982 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 15)
    - A Celebration: American Landscape Painting, Genre Art, & Drawing (2 folders), 1983 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 16-17)
    - Struggle for a Continent: Francis Parkman's "France & England in North America" (2 folders), 1983 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 18-19)
    - Firefighting on Parade, 1983 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 20)
    - New York Themes: Paintings & Etchings by William Meyerowitz & Theresa Bernstein (5 folders), 1983 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 21-25)
    - Lights, Camera, Action: New York's Silent Film Studios, 1983 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 26)
    - The Egon and Hildegard Neustadt Collection of Tiffany Glass. Oversize, 1983 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 16)
      Includes six blueline drawings of the gallery lay-out and design elements.
    - The Adirondacks: A Wilderness Preserved, 1984 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 27)
    - Five New York Families (2 folders), 1984 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 28-29)
    - Visions of Liberty (3 folders), 1984 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 30-32)
    - Lost in a Shuffle: Playing Cards & Board Games, 1984 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 33)
    - The City Comes of Age, 1984 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 34)
      Includes color slides of installation.
    - Baroness Hyde de Neuville: Sketches of America, 1984 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 35)
    - Karol Kowalski, 1985 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 36)
    - Metropolis in Mourning: Ulysses S. Grant (3 folders), 1985 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 1-3)
    - Centuries of Childhood (3 folders), 1985 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 4-6)
      Includes color slides of the installation.
    - Audubon's Birds of North America: The Original Watercolors (3 folders), 1985 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 7-9)
    - Statue of Liberty Centennial Celebration, 1985 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 10)
    - Chicago and New York: Architectural Interaction (4 folders), 1985 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 11-14)
    - Artist in Residence: The North Country Art of Frederic Remington, 1985 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 15)
    - Niagara: Two Centuries of Changing Attitude (10 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 16-25)
    - Prized Prints (8 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 26-33)
    - P.T. Barnum (6 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 34-39)
    - Liberty's Legacy: Photographs of New York's Ethnic Festivals (8 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 40-47)
    - James Henry Cafferty, 1986 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 48)
    - Treasures of Botanical Illustrations (6 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 49-54)
    - Storied Shores: Lake George in Legend & History (4 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 55-58)
    - Proposed Exhibition. Robert Fulton, 1986 (Offsite-box 200, Folder 1)
    - Portraits of Power: Paintings from the Collection of the New York Chamber of Commerce & Industry (7 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 200, Folder 2-8)
    - Made for New York: Antique Toys from the Lawrence Scripps Wilkinson Collection (10 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 200, Folder 9-18)
    - Made for New York: Antique Toys from the Lawrence Scripps Wilkinson Collection. Oversize, 1986 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 16)
      Includes one blueline drawing of design elements.
    - A Portrait of Livingston Manor (9 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 200, Folder 19-27)
    - The Pleasure of Your Company: Parties & Balls in New York City (2 folders), 1986 (Offsite-box 200, Folder 28-29)
    - Jackie Robinson: An American Journey (9 folders), 1987 (Offsite-box 200, Folder 30-38)
    - Audubon: Selected Breeding Birds of New York State, 1987 (Offsite-box 200, Folder 39)
    - Strong on Music: The New York Music Scene (5 folders), 1987 (Offsite-box 201, Folder 1-5)
    - Ex Libris Rufus King (2 folders), 1987 (Offsite-box 201, Folder 6-7)
    - Government by Choice: Inventing the United States Constitution (20 folders), 1987 (Offsite-box 201, Folder 8-27)
      Includes color slides of the installation. Several of the folders are labeled as Are We To Be a Nation? The Making of the Federal Constitution, which was the exhibition held at New York Public Library to which N-YHS loaned objects. These folders include some of the related loan documents, but principally include more Government by Choice documents.
    - Government by Choice: Inventing the United States Constitution. Oversize, 1987 (Box 274, Folder 6)
      Includes design plans by Leone Design Group and sponsor (Country Home Magazine) poster for the lecture series.
    - Government by Choice: Inventing the United States Constitution. Oversize, 1987 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 16)
      Includes two blueline drawings of the gallery lay-out.
    - Jasper Cropsey: Artist & Architect (10 folders), 1987 (Offsite-box 201, Folder 28-37)
    - Jasper Cropsey: Artist & Architect. Oversize, 1987 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 16)
      Includes four blueline drawings of design elements.
    - New York Bestiary: Pets & Pests of Metropolis (5 folders), 1987 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 1-5)
    - The Wagstaff Collection of American Silver (10 folders), 1987 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 6-15)
    - The Wagstaff Collection of American Silver. Oversize, 1987 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 16)
      Includes two blueline drawings of design elements.
    - Hudson River and the Highlands: Photographs by Robert Glenn Ketchum (8 folders), 1987 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 16-23)
    - The Blizzard of '88 (2 folders), 1988 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 24-25)
    - Bellows, Bobbins, & Butterchurns: Keeping House in 19th Century America (7 folders), 1988 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 26-32)
    - Francis W. Edmonds: American Master in the Dutch Tradition (11 folders), 1988 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 33-43)
    - Artistic Houses: Lavish Interiors of 19th Century New York (5 folders), 1988 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 44-48)
    - The Rise & Fall of New York: Building & Unbuilding Manhattan (9 folders), 1988 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 49-57)
    - The Invisible Surface: Paper & the Printing Arts in Early America (4 folders), 1988 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 1-4)
    - Arnold Newman (7 folders), 1988 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 5-11)
    - Hard Cider & Hot Air (5 folders), 1988 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 12-16)
    - Celebrating the Holidays in New York (9 folders), 1988 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 17-25)
    - Celebrating the Holidays in New York. Oversize, 1988 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 16)
    - The Belknap Collection of Silver & Portraits (6 folders), 1988 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 26-31)
    - Burr McIntosh: Polite Society (5 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 32-36)
    - Flag Paintings of Childe Hassam (Hurry for Old Glory), 1989 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 37-43)
    - George Washington in New York (9 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 44-52)
    - Irving Browning (2 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 53-54)
    - Posters by Edward Penfield (3 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 55-57)
    - Cased Images: The 150th Anniversary of Photography (2 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 58-59)
    - An American Sampler: Folk Art from the Shelburne Museum (9 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 60-68)
    - An American Sampler: Folk Art from the Shelburne Museum. Oversize, 1989 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 16)
      Includes one blueline drawing of the gallery lay-out.
    - Beth Israel Hospital Centennial (3 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 203, Folder 69-71)
    - Calyo (7 folders), 1990 (Offsite-box 204, Folder 1-7)
    - Below the Line: Living Poor in America (7 folders), 1990 (Offsite-box 204, Folder 8-14)
    - Paris 1889: American Artists at the Universal Exposition (8 folders), 1990 (Offsite-box 204, Folder 15-22)
    - World War II Posters, 1990 (Offsite-box 204, Folder 23)
    - Thomas Jefferson Bryan: Changing Attributions (3 folders), 1990 (Offsite-box 204, Folder 24-27)
    - Manhattan Contrasts: 20th Century Paintings of New York (2 folders), 1990 (Offsite-box 204, Folder 28-29)
    - Charles Gilbert Hine: Impressions of a City (3 folders), 1990 (Offsite-box 204, Folder 30-32)
    - Luman Reed Gallery (13 folders), 1990 (Offsite-box 204, Folder 33-45)
    - Imagining the New World: Columbian Iconography (3 folders), 1991 (Offsite-box 204, Folder 46-48)
    - Imagining the New World: Columbian Iconography (12 folders), 1991 (Offsite-box 205, Folder 1-12)
    - Imagining the New World: Columbian Iconography. Oversize, 1991 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 16)
    - While They Fought: The Home Front in New York City (2 folders), 1991 (Offsite-box 206, Folder 1-2)
    - Dreams & Shadows: Thomas H. Hotchkiss in 19th Century Italy (13 folders), 1991 (Offsite-box 206, Folder 3-15)
      Includes color slides of objects.
    - Native Americans in American Art & Culture (5 folders, 1991 (Offsite-box 206, Folder 16-20)
    - Views & Visionaries in 19th Century America: Paintings from the Collection of The Century Association, 1992 (Offsite-box 206, Folder 21)
    - Ansel Adams (2 folders), 1992 (Offsite-box 206, Folder 22-23)
    - Victorian Pleasures: 19th Century Board & Table Games (6 folders), 1992 (Offsite-box 206, Folder 24-29)
    - Building City Hall: Competition, Construction, & Context (John McComb) (4 folders), 1992 (Offsite-box 207, Folder 1-4)
    - Party Time: Presidential Campaigns Since 1832 (5 folders), 1992 (Offsite-box 207, Folder 5-9)
    - Stonewall History Project (7 folders), 1992 (Offsite-box 207, Folder 10-16)
      Includes early planning documents from 1992 for a targeted 1994 series of commemorations.
    - The Names Project AIDS Memorial Quilt (8 folders), 1992 (Offsite-box 207, Folder 17-24)
      Includes comments book.
    - A Forest Forever: Art & the Adirondacks (11 folders), 1992 (Offsite-box 207, Folder 25-35)
    - Mother Goose in New York: McLoughlin Books & the Art of Woodcut Illustration (5 folders), 1992 (Offsite-box 208, Folder 1-5)
    - Rembrandt Peale: Career of an American Artist (5 folders), 1993 (Offsite-box 208, Folder 6-10)
    - Exhibition at Sony Corporation (5 folders), 1993 (Offsite-box 208, Folder 11-15)
    - Proposed Reinstallation of the Permanent Collection (10 folders), 1993 (Offsite-box 208, Folder 16-25)
      Includes material concerning a reinstallation that did not occur at this time. A working title for the reinstallation appears to have been Preserving History: Patronage and Collecting at the New-York Historical Society. This working title was similar to the working title Painting and Patronage for the proposed, but never installed, exhibition concerning the Tenth Street Studio (see below). Consequently, the files for each seem to have been confused with documents for both matters in one or the other's files. During processing in 2016, the archivist attempted to sort these out, but some mixture likely remains. Accordingly, researchers interested in the permanent installation (Patronage and Collecting) should also refer to the Tenth Street files (Painting and Patronage), and vice versa.
    - Painting and Patronage: The Tenth Street Studios (11 of 19 folders), 1993 (Offsite-box 208, Folder 26-36)
      Includes working files, likely those principally of curator Annette Blaugrund, for a proposed exhibition that was initially targeted for 1993 or 1994, but was postponed to 1996 or 1997. It appears to have never been installed at N-YHS, though N-YHS loaned objects to an exhibition of this title curated by Blaugrund in 1997 at the Parrish Museum of Art and the National Academy Museum and School of Fine Arts. An alternative working title was Show and Sell: The Marketing of Art in the Tenth Street Studio Building. The principal working title of Painting and Patronage for exhibition was similar enough to the working title of N-YHS's planned reinstallation of the permanent collection that the files for each seem to have been confused with documents for both matters in one or the other's files. During processing in 2016, the archivist attempted to sort these out, but some mixture likely remains. Accordingly, researchers interested in the Tenth Street files (Painting and Patronage) should also refer to the permanent installation files (Patronage and Collecting), and vice versa.
    - Painting and Patronage: The Tenth Street Studios (8 of 19 folders), 1993 (Offsite-box 209, Folder 1-8)
    - 19th Century American Masterworks from N-YHS / Exhibition at The Equitable Gallery (7 folders), 1994 (Offsite-box 209, Folder 9-15)
    - The Grand American Avenue / On the Avenue, Fifth Avenue (9 folders), 1995 (Offsite-box 209, Folder 16-24)
    - Thomas Cole: Landscape into History (11 folders), 1995 (Offsite-box 209, Folder 25-35)
      Originally planned for installation at N-YHS, but because of building renovations at the time, the exhibition was installed at the Brooklyn Museum in partnership with N-YHS.
    - Wrought in Common Clay: New York Stoneware from N-YHS Collections (2 folders), 1995 (Offsite-box 279)
    - Treasury of the Past (12 folders), 1995 (Offsite-box 210, Folder 1-12)